I am multidisciplinary.
أنا متخصص في العديد من المجالات.
As a scientist, I've been a crew commander for a NASA Mars simulation last year,
كعالم، كنت قائد الطاقم لبرنامج محاكاة المريخ بناسا العام الماضي،
and as an artist, I create multicultural community art all over the planet.
وكفنان، أخلق مجتمعًا فنيًا متعدد الثقافات حول العالم.
And recently, I've actually been combining both.
ومؤخرًا، قمت بالجمع بين كليهما بالفعل.
But let me first talk a little more about that NASA mission.
ولكن، لنتحدّث أولًا عن مهمة ناسا تلك.
This is the HI-SEAS program.
هذا هو برنامج "HI-SEAS".
HI-SEAS is a NASA-funded planetary surface analogue
إنه تناظر لسطوح الكواكب بتمويل من ناسا
on the Mauna Loa volcano in Hawaii,
لبركان ماونا لوا في هاواي،
and it's a research program that is specifically designed
وهو برنامج أبحاث تم تصميمه خصيصًا
to study the effects of long-term isolation of small crews.
لدراسة آثار الانعزال طويل المدى للأطقم الصغيرة.
I lived in this dome for four months with a crew of six,
عشت في هذه القبة لمدة أربعة شهور مع طاقم مكون من ستة أشخاص،
a very interesting experience, of course.
تجربة ممتعة جدًا بالطبع.
We did all kinds of research.
قمنا بجميع أنواع الأبحاث.
Our main research was actually a food study,
كان بحثنا الأساسي في الحقيقة دراسة الغذاء،
but apart from that food study --
ولكن بعيدًا عن دراسة الغذاء تلك --
developing a new food system for astronauts living in deep space --
تطوير نظام غذائي جديد لرواد الفضاء الذين يعيشون في فضاء عميق --
we also did all kinds of other research.
قمنا أيضًا بجميع أنواع البحث الأخرى.
We did extra-vehicular activities, as you can see here,
قمنا بنشاطات خارج المركبة، كما ترون هنا،
wearing mock-up space suits,
مرتدين بدلات الفضاء النموذجية،
but we also had our chores and lots of other stuff to do,
كان علينا القيام بالأعمال الروتينية وأشياء أخرى كثيرة،
like questionnaires at the end of every day.
كالاستبيانات في نهاية كل يوم.
Busy, busy work.
عمل كثير جدًا.
Now, as you can imagine,
الآن، كما تتخيلون،
it's quite challenging to live with just a small group of people
إنه من الشاق جدًا العيش مع مجموعة صغيرة فحسب من الناس
in a small space for a long time.
في مساحة صغيرة لفترة طويلة.
There's all kinds of psychological challenges:
توجد كل أنواع التحديات النفسية:
how to keep a team together in these circumstances;
كيف تبقي الفريق متماسكًا تحت هذه الظروف؛
how to deal with the warping of time you start to sense
كيف تتعامل مع التشوه الزمني الذي تبدأ بالإحساس به
when you're living in these circumstances;
عندنا تقوم بالعيش تحت هذه الظروف؛
sleep problems that arise; etc.
مشاكل النوم التي تظهر؛ وغير ذلك.
But also we learned a lot.
ولكننا تعلمنا كثيرًا.
I learned a lot about how individual crew members
تعلمتُ الكثير عن كيف لأعضاء الطاقم
actually cope with a situation like this;
أن يتغلبوا فعلًا على وضع كهذا؛
how you can keep a crew productive and happy,
كيف يمكنك أن تبقي الطاقم منتجًا وسعيدًا،
for example, giving them a good deal of autonomy
مثلًا، أن تعطيهم قدرًا كبيرًا من الاستقلال
is a good trick to do that;
هو وسيلة جيدة لفعل ذلك؛
and honestly, I learned a lot about leadership,
وبصدق، تعلمت الكثير عن القيادة،
because I was a crew commander.
لأنني كنت قائد الطاقم.
So doing this mission,
إذًا بفعل ذلك،
I really started thinking more deeply about our future in outer space.
بدأت فعلًا بالتفكير بشكل أعمق بشأن مستقبلنا في الفضاء الخارجي.
We will venture into outer space, and we will start inhabiting outer space.
سنغامر في الفضاء الخارجي، وسنبدأ بالسكن في الفضاء الخارجي.
I have no doubt about it.
لا أشك في ذلك.
It might take 50 years or it might take 500 years,
ربما يتطلب الأمر 50 أو 500 عام،
but it's going to happen nevertheless.
ولكنه سيحدث بالرغم من ذلك.
So I came up with a new art project called Seeker.
إذًا فأنا ابتكرتُ مشروعًا فنيًا جديدًا يدعى الباحث "سيكر".
And the Seeker project is actually challenging communities all over the world
ومشروع الباحث هذا في الحقيقة يتحدى المجتمعات في أرجاء العالم
to come up with starship prototypes
لابتكار نماذج أصلية لسفن فضاء
that re-envision human habitation and survival.
تعيد تصور سكن الإنسان وبقائه.
That's the core of the project.
ذلك هو جوهر المشروع.
Now, one important thing:
الآن، من المهم أن تعلموا:
This is not a dystopian project.
هذا ليس مشروعًا ضد المدينة الفاضلة.
This is not about, "Oh my God, the world is going wrong
ليس الأمر على غرار: "يا إلهي، العالم يسير بالاتجاه الخاطئ
and we have to escape because we need another future somewhere else."
وعلينا أن نهرب لأننا نحتاج مستقبلًا آخر في مكان ما غير هذا".
No, no.
لا، لا..
The project is basically inviting people
المشروع يدعو الناس ببساطة
to take a step away from earthbound constraints
لأخذ خطوة بعيدًا عن القيود الأرضية
and, as such, reimagine our future.
و، ضمنيًا، إعادة تصور مستقبلنا.
And it's really helpful, and it works really well,
وهذا مفيد حقًا، وهو مُجدي بشكل كبير جدًا،
so that's really the important part of what we're doing.
لذا فهذا بالطبع هو الجزء المهم فيما نفعله.
Now, in this project, I'm using a cocreation approach,
الآن، في هذا المشروع، أقوم باستخدام المنهج الإنشاء المساعد،
which is a slightly different approach
وهو منهج مختلف بعض الشيء
from what you would expect from many artists.
عما سنتوقعه من الكثير من الفنانين.
I'm essentially dropping a basic idea into a group, into a community,
إنه أساسًا يدخل فكرة بسيطة إلى مجموعة، إلى مجتمع،
people start gravitating to the idea,
فيبدأ الناس بالانجذاب إلى الفكرة،
and together, we shape and build the artwork.
ومعًا، نقوم بتشكيل وبناء العمل الفني.
It's a little bit like termites, really.
إنه يشبه النمل الأبيض قليلًا، حقًا.
We just work together,
نحن فقط نعمل سوية،
and even, for example, when architects visit what we're doing,
وحتى، على سبيل المثال، عندما يزور المهندسون ما نفعله،
sometimes they have a bit of a hard time understanding
أحيانًا يواجهون بعض الصعوبة في فهم
how we build without a master plan.
ما نقوم بنائه دون خطة أولية.
We always come up with these fantastic large-scale scupltures
نحن نأتي دومًا بهذه المجسمات الكبيرة الرائعة
that actually we can also inhabit.
التي يمكننا أن نسكنها بالفعل.
The first version was done in Belgium and Holland.
تم بناء أول نسخة في بلجيكا وهولندا.
It was built with a team of almost 50 people.
و قد قام فريق مكون من حوالي 50 شخص ببنائها.
This is the second iteration of that same project,
هذه هي الإعادة الثانية لنفس المشروع،
but in Slovenia, in a different country,
ولكنها في سلوفينيا، في دولة مختلفة،
and the new group was like, we're going to do the architecture differently.
و قد قامت المجموعة الجديدة بعمل الهيكلة بشكل مختلف.
So they took away the architecture, they kept the base of the artwork,
إذًا فهم أزالوا الهيكل، وأبقوا على أساس العمل الفني،
and they built an entirely new,
وقاموا ببناء هيكل جديد كليًا،
much more biomorphic architecture on top of that.
وأكثر حيوية في الشكل فوقه.
And that's another crucial part of the project.
وهذا جزء آخر مهم من المشروع.
It's an evolving artwork, evolving architecture.
إنه عمل فني متطور، هيكلة متطورة.
This was the last version that was just presented a few weeks ago in Holland,
هذه كانت النسخة الأخيرة التي تم تقديمها قبل أسابيع قليلة في هولندا،
which was using caravans as modules to build a starship.
والتي كانت تستعمل البيوت المتنقلة "الكارافانات" كنماذج لبناء سفينة الفضاء.
We bought some second-hand caravans,
اشترينا بعض "الكارافانات" المستعملة،
cut them open,
وقمنا بفتحها
and reassembled them into a starship.
وإعادة تجميعها لبناء سفينة فضاء.
Now, when we're thinking about starships,
الآن، عندما نفكر بشأن سفن الفضاء،
we're not just approaching it as a technological challenge.
لا نقترب منها فقط كتحدٍ تكنولوجي.
We're really looking at it as a combination of three systems:
نحن بالفعل ننظر إليها كمجموع ثلاثة أنظمة:
ecology, people and technology.
علم البيئة والناس والتكنولوجيا.
So there's always a strong ecological component in the project.
لذا هناك دومًا مكوِّن بيئي قوي في هذا المشروع.
Here you can see aquaponic systems
بإمكانكم هنا رؤية الأنظمة الزراعية المائية
that are actually surrounding the astronauts,
التي تحيط رواد الفضاء فعلًا،
so they're constantly in contact with part of the food that they're eating.
لذا فهي متصلة باستمرار بجزء من الغذاء الذي تتناوله.
Now, a very typical thing for this project
الآن، شيء نموذجي جدًا بالنسبة لهذا المشروع
is that we run our own isolation missions inside these art and design projects.
هو أننا ننفذ مهمات العزل خاصتنا داخل مشاريع التصميم والفن هذه.
We actually lock ourselves up for multiple days on end,
إننا في الحقيقة نقوم بسجن أنفسنا لعدة أيام بأكملها،
and test what we build.
ونختبر ما نقوم ببنائه.
And this is, for example,
وهذا، على سبيل المثال،
on the right hand side you can see an isolation mission
على الجانب الأيمن تستطيعون رؤية مهمة العزل
in the Museum of Modern Art in Ljubljana in Slovenia,
داخل متحف الفن الحديث في لجبلجانا في سلوفاكيا،
where six artists and designers locked themselves up --
حيث قام ستة رسامين ومصممين بحبس أنفسهم --
I was part of that --
كنت جزءًا من ذلك --
for four days inside the museum.
لمدة أربعة أيام داخل المتحف.
And, of course, obviously, this is a very performative
وبالطبع، من الواضح، هذه خبرة عملية
and very strong experience for all of us.
وقوية جدًا بالنسبة لنا جميعًا.
Now, the next version of the project is currently being developed
الآن، يتم العمل حاليًا على تطوير النسخة القادمة من المشروع
together with Camilo Rodriguez-Beltran, who is also a TED Fellow,
بصحبة كاميلو رودريغز بلتران، وهو أيضًا زميل TED،
in the Atacama Desert in Chile, a magical place.
في صحراء أتاكاما في تشيلي، مكان ساحر.
First of all, it's really considered a Mars analogue.
في البداية، فقد اعتبرت بالفعل نظيرة المريخ.
It really does look like Mars in certain locations
إنها تشبه المريخ في أماكن معينة
and has been used by NASA to test equipment.
وقد استخدمتها وكالة ناسا لفحص المعدات.
And it has a long history of being connected to space
ولها تاريخ طويل مع اتصالها بالفضاء
through observations of the stars.
من خلال مراقبة النجوم.
It's now home to ALMA,
إنها الآن مقر لـ "ALMA"،
the large telescope that's being developed there.
التلسكوب الضخم الذي يتم تطويره هناك.
But also, it's the driest location on the planet,
ولكن أيضًا، فإنها أكثر المواقع جفافًا على الكوكب،
and that makes it extremely interesting to build our project,
وهذا ما يجعل بناء مشروعنا مثيرًا جدًا للاهتمام،
because suddenly, sustainability is something we have to explore fully.
لأنه فجأة، الاستدامة شيء يجب علينا اكتشافه بالكامل.
We have no other option,
ليس لدينا خيار آخر،
so I'm very curious to see what's going to happen.
لذا أنا مهتم جدًا لرؤية ما سيحدث.
Now, a specific thing for this particular version of the project
الآن، شيء خاص لهذه النسخة من المشروع
is that I'm very interested to see
هو أنني مهتم برؤية
how we can connect with the local population,
كيف يمكن لنا الاتصال بالسكان المحليين،
the native population.
السكان الأصليين.
These people have been living there for a very long time
لقد عاش هؤلاء الناس هناك لوقت طويل جدًا
and can be considered experts in sustainability,
ويمكن اعتبارهم خبراء في الاستدامة،
and so I'm very interested to see what we can learn from them,
ولذا فأنا مهتم برؤية ما نستطيع تعلمه منهم،
and have an input of indigenous knowledge into space exploration.
وأن نمتلك معلومات من العلم الذي يعرفه أصحاب الأرض في استكشاف الفضاء.
So we're trying to redefine how we look at our future in outer space
لذا فإننا نحاول إعادة تعريف كيفية نظرنا إلى مستقبلنا في الفضاء الخارجي
by exploring integration, biology, technology and people;
باستكشاف الدمج والأحياء والتقنية والناس؛
by using a cocreation approach;
باستخدام منهج الإنشاء المساعد؛
and by using and exploring local traditions
وباستخدام واستكشاف التقاليد المحلية
and to see how we can learn from the past and integrate that into our deep future.
ولرؤية كيف نستطيع التعلم من الماضي وندمج ذلك في مستقبلنا الغامض.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)